I want to talk to you today a little bit
أود أن أحدثكم اليوم
about predictable irrationality.
عن اللاعقلانية التي يمكن التنبؤ بها
And my interest in irrational behavior
وقد بدأ اهتمامي بالسلوك غير العقلاني
started many years ago in the hospital.
منذ عدة أعوام حين كنت في المستشفى.
I was burned very badly.
كنت قد أصبت بحروق بالغة السوء
And if you spend a lot of time in hospital,
ولاحظ أنك لو قضيت وقتا طويلا في مستشفى
you'll see a lot of types of irrationalities.
فستلاحظ الكثير والكثير من اللاعقلانية.
And the one that particularly bothered me in the burn department
وكانت مما لاحظته في قسم الحروق من لاعقلانية وضايقتني جدا
was the process by which the nurses took the bandage off me.
هي الطريقة التي تنزع الممرضات بها الضمادات عني.
Now, you must have all taken a Band-Aid off at some point,
بالطبع، جميعكم مر بتجربة نزع ضمادة في مرة من المرات
and you must have wondered what's the right approach.
وبالتأكيد فكرتم في الطريقة الصحيحة لنزعها.
Do you rip it off quickly -- short duration but high intensity --
هل تنزعها سريعا؟ مدة قصيرة مع ألم شديد
or do you take your Band-Aid off slowly --
أم تنزعها ببطء
you take a long time, but each second is not as painful --
فتأخذ وقتا أطول، لكن لا تتعرض لمقدار كبير من الألم في الثانية الواحدة؟
which one of those is the right approach?
أيهما أفضل؟
The nurses in my department thought that the right approach
ظنت الممرضات في قسم الحروق أن الطريقة الأفضل
was the ripping one, so they would grab hold and they would rip,
هي النزع بسرعة، فكانوا يمسكون بالضمادة وينزعوها سريعا،
and they would grab hold and they would rip.
ثم يمسكون بأخرى وينزعوها سريعا
And because I had 70 percent of my body burned, it would take about an hour.
ولأن 70 في المائة من جسمي كان محروقا، فكانت العملية تستغرق حوالي ساعة.
And as you can imagine,
وكما يمكنكم أن تتخيلوا
I hated that moment of ripping with incredible intensity.
كنت أكره لحظة نزع الضمادة بصورة كبيرة
And I would try to reason with them and say,
وكنت أحاول أن أناقشهم في ذلك قائلا
"Why don't we try something else?
لماذا لا نجرب طريقة أخرى؟
Why don't we take it a little longer --
لماذا لا نأخذ وقتا أطول --
maybe two hours instead of an hour -- and have less of this intensity?"
ساعتان مثلا بدلا من ساعة -- لتخفيف الألم قليلا؟
And the nurses told me two things.
فكانت الممرضات ترد بشيئين
They told me that they had the right model of the patient --
أخبروني بأن لديهم النموذج الصحيح للمريض--
that they knew what was the right thing to do to minimize my pain --
وأنهم يعرفون ما هو الشئ الصحيح ليفعلوه لتقليل ألمي--
and they also told me that the word patient doesn't mean
وأخبروني كذلك أن كلمة مريض لا تعنى
to make suggestions or to interfere or ...
أن أقدم مقترحات أو أن أتدخل أو ...
This is not just in Hebrew, by the way.
هذا ليس باللغة العبرية فقط ، بالمناسبة.
It's in every language I've had experience with so far.
إنه في كل اللغات التي تعاملت معها حتى الآن.
And, you know, there's not much -- there wasn't much I could do,
وكما تعلمون، ليس هناك الكثير -- لم يكن لدي الكثير لأفعله،
and they kept on doing what they were doing.
ولقد واصلوا ما كانوا يفعلونه.
And about three years later, when I left the hospital,
وبعد ثلاثة سنوات لاحقة، عندما غادرت المستشفى،
I started studying at the university.
بدأت في الدراسة في الجامعة،
And one of the most interesting lessons I learned
وأحد الدروس الممتعة التي تعلمتها
was that there is an experimental method
كانت هو أن هناك أسلوب تجريبي
that if you have a question you can create a replica of this question
بحيث إن كان لديك سؤالاً يمكنك عمل نسخة طبق الأصل من هذا السؤال
in some abstract way, and you can try to examine this question,
بطريقة ما تجريدية، ويمكنك محاولة إختبار هذا السؤال،
maybe learn something about the world.
ربما تتعلم شيئاً عن العالم.
So that's what I did.
لذا فقد قمت بذلك.
I was still interested
ومازلت مهتماً
in this question of how do you take bandages off burn patients.
بهذا السؤال حول هل يمكنك أخذ الضمادات من جروح المرضى.
So originally I didn't have much money,
إذاً ففي الأساس ليس لدي الكثير من المال،
so I went to a hardware store and I bought a carpenter's vice.
لذا فقد ذهبت لمتجر أجهزة حاسوب وأشتريت مقبض نجار.
And I would bring people to the lab and I would put their finger in it,
وأقوم بجلب الناس إلى المختبر وأضع أصبعهم عليها،
and I would crunch it a little bit.
وأقوم بالضغط قليلاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I would crunch it for long periods and short periods,
وأقوم بالضغط عليها لفترات طويلة وفترات قصيرة،
and pain that went up and pain that went down,
والألم الذي يرتفع والألم الذي يقل،
and with breaks and without breaks -- all kinds of versions of pain.
وبفترات راحة وبدون فترات راحة -- كل أنواع النماذج للألم.
And when I finished hurting people a little bit, I would ask them,
وعندما أنتهيت من تسبيب الألم للناس قليلاً، أسالهم،
so, how painful was this? Or, how painful was this?
إذاً، كم كان هذا مؤلماً؟ أو ، كم هو مؤلم؟
Or, if you had to choose between the last two,
أو، إن كنت سأختار بين الخيارين الأخيرين،
which one would you choose?
أي واحد منهما ستختار؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I kept on doing this for a while.
واصلت في عمل هذا لفترة.
And then, like all good academic projects, I got more funding.
ثم، مثل كل المشاريع الأكاديمية الجيدة، حصلت على مزيد من التمويل.
I moved to sounds, electrical shocks --
وانتقلت إلى الأصوات، الصدمات الكهربائية--
I even had a pain suit that I could get people to feel much more pain.
حتى أنني حصلت على بدلة ألم بحيث أستطيع تسبيب ألم أكثر للناس.
But at the end of this process,
لكن بنهاية هذه العملية،
what I learned was that the nurses were wrong.
ما تعلمته كان أن الممرضات كنّ على خطأ.
Here were wonderful people with good intentions
هنا حيث الناس الرائعون بنوايا حسنة
and plenty of experience, and nevertheless
وخبرة كبيرة، ومع ذلك
they were getting things wrong predictably all the time.
كانوا يفعلون أشياء خاطئة طوال الوقت كما أتوقع.
It turns out that because we don't encode duration
وقد وضح أنه لأننا لا نقوم بترميز المدة
in the way that we encode intensity,
بالطريقة التي نرمز بها الكثافة،
I would have had less pain if the duration would have been longer
كنت سأحصل على ألم أقل إن كانت الفترة أطول
and the intensity was lower.
والكثافة أقل.
It turns out it would have been better to start with my face,
وقد وضح أنه سيكون أفضل أن أبدأ بوجهي،
which was much more painful, and move toward my legs,
الذي كان أكثر ألماً بكثير، والإنتقال نحو رجليّ،
giving me a trend of improvement over time --
يعطي إتجاه بالتحسن عبر الزمن --
that would have been also less painful.
وذلك سيكون أيضاً أقل ألماً بكثير.
And it also turns out that it would have been good
وقد وضح أيضاً أنه سيكون جيداً
to give me breaks in the middle to kind of recuperate from the pain.
لإعطائي فترات راحة في المنتصف لنوعاً ما للتعافي من الألم.
All of these would have been great things to do,
كل هذه كانت أشياء جيدة لتفعلها،
and my nurses had no idea.
ولم تكن للمرضات أي فكرة.
And from that point on I started thinking,
ومن تلك النقطة وبعدها بدأت بالتفكير،
are the nurses the only people in the world who get things wrong
هل الممرضات هن الوحيدات في العالم لا يفهمون هذه الأشياء
in this particular decision, or is it a more general case?
في هذا القرار تحديداً، أم أنها حالة أكثر عموميةً؟
And it turns out it's a more general case --
وقد وضح أنها أكثر عموميةً--
there's a lot of mistakes we do.
هناك الكثير من الأخطاء التي نفعلها.
And I want to give you one example of one of these irrationalities,
وأريد أن أعطيكم مثالاً لهذه الأشياء اللاعقلانية،
and I want to talk to you about cheating.
وأريد أن أتحدث عن الغش.
And the reason I picked cheating is because it's interesting,
والسبب أنني أخترت الغش هو لأنه مثير،
but also it tells us something, I think,
وهو أيضاً يخبرنا بشئ، كما أعتقد،
about the stock market situation we're in.
حول حال سوق الأسهم الذي نحن فيه.
So, my interest in cheating started
لذا، فقد بدأ إهتمامي بالكذب
when Enron came on the scene, exploded all of a sudden,
حينما جاء إنرون إلى المشهد، وإنفجر فجأةً،
and I started thinking about what is happening here.
وقد بدأت بالتفكير حول ما الذي يحدث هنا.
Is it the case that there was kind of
هل هو الحال أننا نوعا ما
a few apples who are capable of doing these things,
قليل من الأشخاص قادرين على فعل هذه الأشياء،
or are we talking a more endemic situation,
أم أننا نتحدث عن حالة متوطنة،
that many people are actually capable of behaving this way?
بحيث أن كثير من الناس قادرون على التصرف بهذه الطريقة؟
So, like we usually do, I decided to do a simple experiment.
لذا، مثلما نفعل عادةً، قررت أن أقوم بتجربة بسيطة
And here's how it went.
وها هي كما مرت.
If you were in the experiment, I would pass you a sheet of paper
إذا كنت في التجربة، كنت سأمرر عليك ورقة
with 20 simple math problems that everybody could solve,
تحوي 20 مسألة حسابية بسيطة يمكن للجميع حلها،
but I wouldn't give you enough time.
لكني لن أعطيكم الوقت الكافي.
When the five minutes were over, I would say,
عندما تنتهي الخمس دقائق، سأقول،
"Pass me the sheets of paper, and I'll pay you a dollar per question."
" مرروا الأوراق لي، وسأعطيكم دولاراً مقابل كل سؤال."
People did this. I would pay people four dollars for their task --
يفعل الناس هذا. سأدفع للناس أربعة دولارات لعملهم--
on average people would solve four problems.
في المتوسط يحل الناس أربعة مسائل.
Other people I would tempt to cheat.
أناس آخرون يحاولون الغش.
I would pass their sheet of paper.
سأمرر أوراقهم.
When the five minutes were over, I would say,
عندما تنتهي الخمس دقائق، سأقول،
"Please shred the piece of paper.
" الرجاء قم بتمزيق الورقة.
Put the little pieces in your pocket or in your backpack,
ضع الجزء الصغير في جيبك الخلفي،
and tell me how many questions you got correctly."
وأخبرني كم عدد الأسئلة التي حللتها بطريقة صحيحة."
People now solved seven questions on average.
الناس الآن قاموا بحل سبعة أسئلة في المتوسط.
Now, it wasn't as if there was a few bad apples --
الآن، الأمر ليس كما وأن هناك القليل من التفاح الفاسد بين الأشخاص --
a few people cheated a lot.
أو أن القليل من الناس غشوا بكثرة.
Instead, what we saw is a lot of people who cheat a little bit.
بل عوضاً عن ذلك، ما شهدناه هو أن الكثير من الناس قاموا بالغش قليلاً.
Now, in economic theory,
الآن، في نظرية الإقتصاد،
cheating is a very simple cost-benefit analysis.
الغش هو عملية تحليل بسيطة للتكلفة والربح.
You say, what's the probability of being caught?
أنت تقول، ما هو إحتمال أن يتم ضبطي؟
How much do I stand to gain from cheating?
كم سأكسب من الغش؟
And how much punishment would I get if I get caught?
كم من العقاب سيواجهني إن تم ضبطي؟
And you weigh these options out --
وتقوم بموازنة هذه الخيارات --
you do the simple cost-benefit analysis,
تقوم بالتحليل البسيط للكلفة والربح،
and you decide whether it's worthwhile to commit the crime or not.
وتقرر سواء كان الأمر يستحق إرتكاب الجريمة أم لا.
So, we try to test this.
لذا، نحاول إختبار هذا.
For some people, we varied how much money they could get away with --
لبعض الناس. قمنا بتنويع كم من المال سيحصلون عليه --
how much money they could steal.
كم من المال يمكنهم الحصول عليه بالغش.
We paid them 10 cents per correct question, 50 cents,
دفعنا لهم 10 سنتات مقابل الإجابة الصحيحة، 50 سنتاً،
a dollar, five dollars, 10 dollars per correct question.
دولاراً، خمسة دولارات، عشر دولارات مقابل الإجابة الصحيحة.
You would expect that as the amount of money on the table increases,
يمكنك توقع أن كلما تزداد كمية المال على الطاولة،
people would cheat more, but in fact it wasn't the case.
سيغش الناس أكثر، لكن في الواقع لم تكن تلك الحالة.
We got a lot of people cheating by stealing by a little bit.
لقد ضبطنا الكثير من الناس يغشون بسرقة القليل.
What about the probability of being caught?
ماذا عن إحتمال ضبطهم متلبسين؟
Some people shredded half the sheet of paper,
بعض الناس قام بتمزيق نصف الورقة،
so there was some evidence left.
لذا فقد خلفوا الدليل.
Some people shredded the whole sheet of paper.
بعض الناس قام بتمزيق كل الورقة.
Some people shredded everything, went out of the room,
بعض الناس قام بتمزيق كل شئ، ذهب خارج الغرفة،
and paid themselves from the bowl of money that had over 100 dollars.
ودفعوا لأنفسهم من وعاء المال الذي فيه أكثر من 100 دولار.
You would expect that as the probability of being caught goes down,
ستتوقع أن إحتمال أن يتم ضبطك متلبساً ينخفض،
people would cheat more, but again, this was not the case.
سيغش الناس أكثر، لكن مجدداً، لم تكن تلك الحالة.
Again, a lot of people cheated by just by a little bit,
مجدداً، غش الكثير من الناس بالقليل،
and they were insensitive to these economic incentives.
ولم يكونوا حساسين لتلك المحفزات الإقتصادية.
So we said, "If people are not sensitive
لذا فقد قلنا، " إن لم يكن الناس حساسين
to the economic rational theory explanations, to these forces,
لشروحات نظرية العقلانية الإقتصادية، لهذه القوى،
what could be going on?"
ما الذي يمكن أن يحدث؟"
And we thought maybe what is happening is that there are two forces.
وفكرنا أن ما يحدث ربما هو أن هناك قوتين.
At one hand, we all want to look at ourselves in the mirror
على جانب، جميعنا يريد النظر لنفسه في المرآة
and feel good about ourselves, so we don't want to cheat.
ويشعر بالحُسن حيال نفسه، لذلك لا نريد الغش.
On the other hand, we can cheat a little bit,
وعلى جانب آخر، يمكننا الغش قليلاً،
and still feel good about ourselves.
وما نزال نشعر بالحُسن حيال أنفسنا.
So, maybe what is happening is that
لذا، ربما ما يحدث هو أن
there's a level of cheating we can't go over,
هناك مستوى من الغش لا يمكننا تخطيه،
but we can still benefit from cheating at a low degree,
لكن ما يزال يمكننا الإستفادة من الغش في اقل درجة،
as long as it doesn't change our impressions about ourselves.
طالما أنه لا يغيّر إنطباعنا حول أنفسنا.
We call this like a personal fudge factor.
نحن نسمي هذا عامل الغش الشخصي.
Now, how would you test a personal fudge factor?
الآن، كيف تختبر عامل الغش الشخصي؟
Initially we said, what can we do to shrink the fudge factor?
مبدئياً نقول، ما الذي يمكننا فعله لتقليص عامل الغش الشخصي؟
So, we got people to the lab, and we said,
إذاً، جلبنا الناس إلى المختبر، وقلنا،
"We have two tasks for you today."
" لدينا مهمتين لكم اليوم."
First, we asked half the people
أولاً، نسأل نصف الناس
to recall either 10 books they read in high school,
ليتذكروا 10 كتب درسوها في الثانوية العليا،
or to recall The Ten Commandments,
أو يتذكروا الوصايا العشر،
and then we tempted them with cheating.
ثم نغريهم بالغش.
Turns out the people who tried to recall The Ten Commandments --
وضح أن الناس الذين حاولوا تذكر الوصايا العشر --
and in our sample nobody could recall all of The Ten Commandments --
وفي عينتنا لم يستطع أي شخص تذكر كل الوصايا العشر --
but those people who tried to recall The Ten Commandments,
لكن أولئك الناس الذين حاولوا تذكر الوصايا العشر،
given the opportunity to cheat, did not cheat at all.
الذين أعطيناهم الفرصة للغش، لم يغشوا بتاتاً.
It wasn't that the more religious people --
الأمر ليس أنهم أكثر تديناً--
the people who remembered more of the Commandments -- cheated less,
الناس الذين تذكروا وصايا أكثر -- غشوا أقل،
and the less religious people --
وأناس أكثر تديناً --
the people who couldn't remember almost any Commandments --
الناس الذين لم يستطيعوا تذكر أي وصية تقريباً --
cheated more.
غشوا أكثر.
The moment people thought about trying to recall The Ten Commandments,
اللحظة التي فكر الناس بمحاولة تذكر الوصايا العشر،
they stopped cheating.
توقفوا عن الغش.
In fact, even when we gave self-declared atheists
في الحقيقة، حتى عندما أعطينا أناس أعلنوا إلحداهم
the task of swearing on the Bible and we give them a chance to cheat,
مهمة القسم على الإنجيل وأعطيناهم الفرصة للغش،
they don't cheat at all.
لم يقوموا بالغش بتاتاً.
Now, Ten Commandments is something that is hard
الآن، الوصايا العشر هي شئ صعب
to bring into the education system, so we said,
إدخاله في النظام التعليمي، لذا فقد قلنا،
"Why don't we get people to sign the honor code?"
" لم لا نجعل الناس يوقعون على ميثاق شرف؟"
So, we got people to sign,
لذا، فقد جعلنا الناس توقع،
"I understand that this short survey falls under the MIT Honor Code."
" أنا أقر أن هذا الإستطلاع القصير يقع ضمن ميثاق الشرف لأم آي تي."
Then they shredded it. No cheating whatsoever.
ثم قاموا بتمزيقه. لا غش مهما حصل.
And this is particularly interesting,
وهذا تحديداً مثير،
because MIT doesn't have an honor code.
لأن أم آي تي ليس لديها ميثاق للشرف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, all this was about decreasing the fudge factor.
لذا، كل ذلك كان حول خفض عامل الغش الشخصي.
What about increasing the fudge factor?
ماذا عن رفع عامل الغش الشخصي؟
The first experiment -- I walked around MIT
أول تجربة -- تمشيت حول أم آي تي
and I distributed six-packs of Cokes in the refrigerators --
ووزعت ست علب من الكولا في الثلاجات--
these were common refrigerators for the undergrads.
هذه ثلاجات عامة لطلاب الجامعة.
And I came back to measure what we technically call
وعندما رجعت لقياس ما نسميه تقنياً
the half-lifetime of Coke -- how long does it last in the refrigerators?
نصف دورة حياة الكولا-- كم ستبقى في الثلاجات؟
As you can expect it doesn't last very long; people take it.
كما يمكنكم أن تتوقعوا لم تصمد طويلاً. أخذها الناس.
In contrast, I took a plate with six one-dollar bills,
على النقيض، أخذت لوحة مع ست ورقات من فئة الدولار،
and I left those plates in the same refrigerators.
وتركت تلك اللوحات في نفس الثلاجات.
No bill ever disappeared.
لم تختفي أي ورقة.
Now, this is not a good social science experiment,
الآن، هذه ليست تجربة جيدة في العلوم الإجتماعية،
so to do it better I did the same experiment
لذا فقد قمت بتنفيذ نفس التجربة بصورة أفضل
as I described to you before.
كما أوضحت لكم سابقاً.
A third of the people we passed the sheet, they gave it back to us.
ثلت الناس الذين مررنا لهم الورقة، قاموا بإرجاعها لنا.
A third of the people we passed it to, they shredded it,
ثلث الناس الذين مررناها لهم، قاموا بتمزيقها،
they came to us and said,
جاءوا إلينا وقالوا،
"Mr. Experimenter, I solved X problems. Give me X dollars."
" يا أستاذ، لقد حللت المسائل "س". أعطني "س" من الدولارات."
A third of the people, when they finished shredding the piece of paper,
ثلث الناس، عندما أنتهوا من تمزيق الورق،
they came to us and said,
جاءوا إلينا وقالوا،
"Mr Experimenter, I solved X problems. Give me X tokens."
" يا أستاذ، لقد حللت المسائل "س". أعطني "س" من الرموز."
We did not pay them with dollars; we paid them with something else.
لم ندفع لهم بالدولارات. دفعنا لهم بشئ آخر.
And then they took the something else, they walked 12 feet to the side,
ثم أخذوا شيئاً آخراً، تمشوا 12 قدماً على الجنب،
and exchanged it for dollars.
وقاموا باستبدالها بالدولارات.
Think about the following intuition.
فكروا حول هذه الفكرة.
How bad would you feel about taking a pencil from work home,
كم هو سيئ شعورك حيال أخذ قلم رصاص من مكان العمل،
compared to how bad would you feel
مقارنة بما هو سيئ شعورك
about taking 10 cents from a petty cash box?
حيال أخذ 10 سنتات من صندوق النقود ؟
These things feel very differently.
الشعور بهذه الأشياء مختلفاً كلياً.
Would being a step removed from cash for a few seconds
هل ستكون خطوة أزيلت من النقد لثواني قليلة
by being paid by token make a difference?
بالدفع لك عبر الرموز ستحدث فارقاً؟
Our subjects doubled their cheating.
قام المشاركين معنا بمضاعفة غشهم.
I'll tell you what I think
وأخبركم بما أفكر به
about this and the stock market in a minute.
حيال هذه وسوق الأسهم خلال دقيقة.
But this did not solve the big problem I had with Enron yet,
لكن هذا لا يحل المشكلة الكبيرة التي لدي مع إنرون بعد،
because in Enron, there's also a social element.
لأن في حالة إنرون، هناك عامل إجتماعي أيضاً.
People see each other behaving.
يرى الناس تصرفات بعضهم البعض.
In fact, every day when we open the news
في الحقيقة، كل يوم عندما تفتح الأخبار
we see examples of people cheating.
نرى نماذج لغش الناس.
What does this cause us?
ماذا يسبب هذا لنا؟
So, we did another experiment.
لذا، فقد قمنا بتجربة أخرى.
We got a big group of students to be in the experiment,
حصلنا على مجموعة كبيرة من الطلاب في التجربة،
and we prepaid them.
وقمنا بالدفع لهم مسبقاً.
So everybody got an envelope with all the money for the experiment,
لذا فقد حصل كلٌ منهم على مظروف مع كل المال للتجربة،
and we told them that at the end, we asked them
وأخبرناهم بأنهم في النهاية، سألناهم
to pay us back the money they didn't make. OK?
ليرجعوا لنا المال الذي لم يكسبوه. حسناً؟
The same thing happens.
نفس الشئ يحدث.
When we give people the opportunity to cheat, they cheat.
عندما تعطي الناس الفرصة للغش، يقومون بالغش.
They cheat just by a little bit, all the same.
يقومون بالغش قليلاً، لكنهم جميعاً نفس الشئ.
But in this experiment we also hired an acting student.
لكن في هذه التجربة قمنا بتوظيف أناس يمثلون أنهم طلاب
This acting student stood up after 30 seconds, and said,
هؤلاء الممثلون دور الطلاب وقفوا بعد 30 ثانية، وقالوا،
"I solved everything. What do I do now?"
" لقد حللت كل شئ. ما الذي عليّ فعله؟"
And the experimenter said, "If you've finished everything, go home.
وقال الممتحن، " إذا أنتهيت من كل شئ، أذهب إلى البيت."
That's it. The task is finished."
ذلك كل شئ. المهمة أنتهت.
So, now we had a student -- an acting student --
إذاً، الآن لدينا طالب -- ممثل دور طالب --
that was a part of the group.
الذي كان جزء من المجموعة.
Nobody knew it was an actor.
ولا أحد يعلم أنه ممثل.
And they clearly cheated in a very, very serious way.
وبكل وضوح قام بالغش، بصورة جدية للغاية.
What would happen to the other people in the group?
ما الذي سيحصل لبقية الناس في المجموعة؟
Will they cheat more, or will they cheat less?
سيغشون أكثر، أم سيغشون أقل؟
Here is what happens.
ها هو ما يحصل.
It turns out it depends on what kind of sweatshirt they're wearing.
لقد وضح، انه يعتمد على نوعية الملبس اللطيف الذي يرتدونه.
Here is the thing.
ها هو شئ.
We ran this at Carnegie Mellon and Pittsburgh.
قمنا بعمل هذا في كارنيج ميلون وبطسبيرج.
And at Pittsburgh there are two big universities,
وفي بطسبيرج هناك جامعتين كبيرتين،
Carnegie Mellon and University of Pittsburgh.
كارنيج مليون وجامعة بطسبيرج.
All of the subjects sitting in the experiment
وكل هؤلاء المشاركون الجالسين في التجربة
were Carnegie Mellon students.
كانوا طلاب من كارنيج ميلون.
When the actor who was getting up was a Carnegie Mellon student --
بينما كان الممثل الذي يقف من طلاب كارينج ميلون--
he was actually a Carnegie Mellon student --
لقد كان بالفعل طالب من كارينج ميلون--
but he was a part of their group, cheating went up.
لكنه كان جزءاً من مجموعتهم، لذا فقد أرتفع الغش.
But when he actually had a University of Pittsburgh sweatshirt,
لكن عندما كان يرتدي قميصاً لجامعة بطسبيرج،
cheating went down.
أنخفض الغش.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, this is important, because remember,
الآن، هذا مهم، لنتذكر،
when the moment the student stood up,
في اللحظة التي وقف فيها الطالب،
it made it clear to everybody that they could get away with cheating,
لقد أصبح واضحاً للجميع أنهم يمكنهم أن يفلتوا مع الغش،
because the experimenter said,
لأن الممتحن قال،
"You've finished everything. Go home," and they went with the money.
" أنتهيت من كل شئ. أذهب للبيت،" وقد ذهبوا بالمال.
So it wasn't so much about the probability of being caught again.
لذا فلم يكن الأمر كثيراً حول إحتمال أن يتم ضبطك مجدداً.
It was about the norms for cheating.
لقد كان حول عادات الغش.
If somebody from our in-group cheats and we see them cheating,
إن كان شخص ما من مجموعتنا يغش ونحن نراه يغش،
we feel it's more appropriate, as a group, to behave this way.
نحس أنه أكثر صحةً، كمجموعة، أن نتصرف بهذه الطريقة.
But if it's somebody from another group, these terrible people --
لكن إن كان شخص من مجموعة أخرى، هؤلاء الناس الفظيعين--
I mean, not terrible in this --
أعني، ليسوا فظيعين في هذا المعنى --
but somebody we don't want to associate ourselves with,
لكن شخص ما لا نريد إلصاق أنفسنا معه،
from another university, another group,
من جامعة أخرى، من مجموعة أخرى،
all of a sudden people's awareness of honesty goes up --
فجأة يرتفع وعي الناس وصدقهم --
a little bit like The Ten Commandments experiment --
قليلاً مثل تجربة الوصايا العشر --
and people cheat even less.
ويغش الناس أقل حتى.
So, what have we learned from this about cheating?
إذاً، ما الذي تعلمناه من هذا حول الغش؟
We've learned that a lot of people can cheat.
لقد تعلمنا أن الكثير من الناس يمكنهم الغش.
They cheat just by a little bit.
يقومون بالغش لأنه قليل جداً.
When we remind people about their morality, they cheat less.
عندما نقوم بتذكير الناس حول الأخلاق، يقومون بغش أقل.
When we get bigger distance from cheating,
عندما نبتعد مسافة أكبر من الغش،
from the object of money, for example, people cheat more.
من عنصر المال، على سبيل المثال، يغش الناس أكثر.
And when we see cheating around us,
وحينما نرى الغش حولنا،
particularly if it's a part of our in-group, cheating goes up.
تحديداً إن كان جزءاً من مجموعتنا، يرتفع الغش.
Now, if we think about this in terms of the stock market,
الآن، إن فكرنا حول هذا بالنسبة لسوق الأسهم،
think about what happens.
فكروا حول ماذا يحدث.
What happens in a situation when you create something
ماذا يحدث في أوضاع عندما ننشئ شيئاً
where you pay people a lot of money
حيث تدفع للناس الكثير من المال
to see reality in a slightly distorted way?
لترى الحقيقة بطريقة أكثر تشويهاً؟
Would they not be able to see it this way?
سيكونوا غير قادرين على رؤيتها بهذه الطريقة؟
Of course they would.
بالتأكيد سيكونوا قادرين.
What happens when you do other things,
ما الذي يحدث عندما تفعل أشياء أخرى،
like you remove things from money?
مثل إزالة الأشياء من "مفهوم" المال ليصبح مجرد أرقام ؟
You call them stock, or stock options, derivatives,
يمكنك تسميتهم أسهم، أو خيارات الأسهم، السندات ،
mortgage-backed securities.
أسهم مدعومة بالقروض العقارية.
Could it be that with those more distant things,
هل يمكن أن يكون الغش أكثر مع هذه الأشياء الأكثر بعداً عن مفهوم المال " المادي "،
it's not a token for one second,
إنها ليست رموزاً لثانية واحدة،
it's something that is many steps removed from money
إنها شيء أزيلت عنه عدة خطوات من " صورة " المال
for a much longer time -- could it be that people will cheat even more?
لفترة طويلة جداً-- هل يمكن أن هذا سبب أن أولئك الناس سوف يغشون أكثر ؟
And what happens to the social environment
وسبب ما يحدث للبيئة الإجتماعية
when people see other people behave around them?
عندما يرى الناس آخرون يتصرفون حولهم بهذه الشاكلة ؟
I think all of those forces worked in a very bad way
أعتقد أن كل ذلك يسيّر العمل بطريقة سيئة للغاية
in the stock market.
في سوق الأسهم.
More generally, I want to tell you something
بتعميم أكبر ، أريد أن أخبركم بشئ
about behavioral economics.
حول الإقتصاد السلوكي.
We have many intuitions in our life,
لدينا العديد من الأفكار في حياتنا،
and the point is that many of these intuitions are wrong.
والفكرة هي أن العديد من هذه الأفكار خاطئة.
The question is, are we going to test those intuitions?
السؤال هو، هل سنقوم بإختبار تلك الأفكار؟
We can think about how we're going to test this intuition
يمكننا التفكير حول كيف يمكننا إختبار هذه الفكرة
in our private life, in our business life,
في حياتنا الخاصة، أو في حياتنا العملية،
and most particularly when it goes to policy,
وأكثر تحديداً حينما يتعلق الأمر بالسياسة،
when we think about things like No Child Left Behind,
ونفكر بأشياء مثل لا نترك طفلاً خلفنا،
when you create new stock markets, when you create other policies --
عندما تنشئ سوقاً جديداً للأسهم، عندما تنشئ سياسات أخرى--
taxation, health care and so on.
الضرائب، الرعايا الصحية وهلمجرا.
And the difficulty of testing our intuition
إن صعوبة إختبار هذه الأفكار
was the big lesson I learned
كانت درساً عظيماً تعلمته
when I went back to the nurses to talk to them.
عندما رجعت إلى تلك الممرضات لأتحدث إليهم.
So I went back to talk to them
لذا، فقد رجعت لهم
and tell them what I found out about removing bandages.
وأخبرتهم ما توصلت إليه حول إزالة الضمادات.
And I learned two interesting things.
وقد تعلمت شيئين مثيرين.
One was that my favorite nurse, Ettie,
أحدهما كان أن ممرضتي المفضلة، إيتتي،
told me that I did not take her pain into consideration.
أخبرتني أنني لم أخذ ما سببته لي من آلالام مأخذ الجد.
She said, "Of course, you know, it was very painful for you.
قالت، " بالطبع، كما تعلم، كان مؤلماً بالنسبة لك.
But think about me as a nurse,
لكن فكر بي كممرضة،
taking, removing the bandages of somebody I liked,
أقوم بأخذ، إزالة الضمادات لكل شخص أرتحت له،
and had to do it repeatedly over a long period of time.
وعليّ فعل ذلك مراراً لفترة طويلة من الزمن.
Creating so much torture was not something that was good for me, too."
مسببة الكثير من العذاب لم يكن شيئاً جيداً بالنسبة لي، أيضاً."
And she said maybe part of the reason was it was difficult for her.
وقد قالت، ربما جزء من السبب كان أنه صعب بالنسبة لها.
But it was actually more interesting than that, because she said,
لكن في الواقع كان أكثر إثارة عن ذلك، لأنها قالت،
"I did not think that your intuition was right.
"أنا لا أعتقد أن فكرتك كانت صائبة.
I felt my intuition was correct."
لقد شعرت بأن فكرتي كانت صائبة."
So, if you think about all of your intuitions,
لذا، فاذا فكرت حول كل أفكارنا،
it's very hard to believe that your intuition is wrong.
فانه صعب تصديق أن فكرتك خاطئة.
And she said, "Given the fact that I thought my intuition was right ..." --
وقد قالت، " بإعتبار حقيقة أنني فكرت أن فكرتك كانت صائبة..."--
she thought her intuition was right --
لقد أعتقدت أن فكرتها كانت صائبة--
it was very difficult for her to accept doing a difficult experiment
لقد كان صعباً جداً بالنسبة لها تقبّل فعل تجربة صعبة
to try and check whether she was wrong.
لمحاولة التأكد سواء كانت مخطئة.
But in fact, this is the situation we're all in all the time.
لكن في الواقع، هذا هو الحال الذي نحن فيه طوال الوقت.
We have very strong intuitions about all kinds of things --
لدينا أفكار قوية للغاية حول كل الأشياء --
our own ability, how the economy works,
مقدرتنا الخاصة، كيف يعمل الإقتصاد،
how we should pay school teachers.
كيف ينبغي أن ندفع لمعلمي المدارس.
But unless we start testing those intuitions,
لكن إن لم نقم بإختبار تلك الأفكار،
we're not going to do better.
فلن نتحسن.
And just think about how better my life would have been
وفقط فكروا حول كيف كانت ستكون حياتي أسعد
if these nurses would have been willing to check their intuition,
إن كان أولئك الممرضات راغبات في التأكد من أفكارهن،
and how everything would have been better
وكيف سيكون كل شئ أفضل
if we just start doing more systematic experimentation of our intuitions.
إن بدأنا فقط بفعل تجارب منهجية على أفكارنا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.